I don't remember the exact date, but it was not long after Trayvon was murdered.
And I'm not a reporter. I don't just create art about everything that happens good or bad.
For me, it feels like there needs to be a value added to use the capitalist terminology.
I approached my work as a medicinal practice.
So really my question is, what can I add that will reinforce people's political clarity, emotional immune system capacity for resistance motivation for resistance.
And after Trayvon was killed, people would ask me, are you going to make a poster about this?
And I didn't hadn't thought about it.
Unfortunately, racist murders are not an uncommon thing in this country.
And there was not anything obvious to say that this particular one would be a turning point in movement history.
As the attention grew, I did my due diligence, I went online and looked around to see, well, what is the arts is being created?
Because that was part of why I was saying, well, maybe not because other people are making art. I don't need to fill avoid if there is no voice.
But what I found was a lot of art that was really steeped in frustration and hopelessness.
And I was honest, but it isn't medicinal.
Those are feelings that are that are very accessible to people and simply reinforcing them doesn't feel like a path to power.
So I started thinking about what to do.
And I found this quote by Ella Baker, well known because of its, you know, use in a song by sweet honey in the rock.
And she said, yes, this has been going on for a long time.
You know, the time that Emmett Till was killed, right.
And yet she's looking ahead to a time when it won't be happening.
Right. So it has that element of we are looking toward a future where this won't be the case.
So that feels medicinal that way I could feel like, okay, this makes sense to make the same age.
Actually, I mean, art for me can take hours. It can take weeks, depending on the piece.
This one I created one evening after supper and I posted it online the next morning, which is unusual, but the I was able to sort of come up with this idea.
This basic image, I use scratch board, which is involves using a knife blade on a clay surface that has ink on it and scraping away to get those block print looking textures.
I don't, I'm not formally trained in art or triture is not a strong point for me sometimes I can, I can really nail it, but it takes me work to get there.
And I was not having really success getting us, you know, working in scratch board and getting it to look like Trayvon Martin.
So I thought, well, I'm going to just try it on a set on a piece of paper using a watercolor and ink, you know, or you ink and water and see if I can come up with something and I came up with this face that looked bright and I simply.
I just light it into this piece of scratch board art. So you have this hard edge woodcutty image within which this softer watercolor looking image and it worked and I put it out there and.
I just struck a chord because it's been used in books and calendars and magazines and it was people printed as signs and carried in protests and Ferguson Missouri after Michael Brown was murdered.
Trayvon's brother reached out through somebody who I had met a mutual acquaintance anyway to ask for a signed copy and it's continued to travel around.
And you know, certainly that's gratifying that it struck a chord to me how many copies are printed, how widely it's used isn't necessarily the measure of success because every medicine has its purpose right there are some posters that will never be blockbuster sellers, but have deep meaning for a particular subset of people who, who part of whose trauma is being unrecognized and unnoticed.
And so for them it's a piece of art can be deeply meaningful even though there ain't a whole lot of people in that in that subculture.
But this one was one that travels widely and I think it's again because it has.
I mean, certainly people respond to the art. I don't have real way of measuring that, but I think an important element it is that it has a seed of hope.
And it's a small seed, it's not a smiley face, it's not saying everything's going to be okay, but it says we are moving toward a future when this doesn't have to happen.
I don't know how the people experience it but I find I find the the face haunting because it feels real to me and that's part of I mean that's one of the subversive things that we do in art, which I'm by no means unique in this regard.
This is done across the board with with effective political art to simply make the subjects of the work human.
Right, not some symbolic victim of oppression, right?
You know,
or so much more than that.